<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A testimony wherein is shewed certain weighty reasons why the national ministers, their way and practice, is conscientiously disowned, and their maintenance by tythes or other hire denyed also, a testimony, from a certain experience, to the people called Presbyterians, and all that are zealous in their way : also, a testimony to them called Anabaptists, with some reflections upon a book (propogated among them), called The child's instructor, .../ by a sufferer for the testimony of truth against deceit, and the antichristian oppression of tythes ... Sebastion Ellythorp.</title>
            <author>Ellythorp, Sebastian, d. 1695.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 70KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 15 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A39314</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">15619451</idno>
  <idno type="VID">104194</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240851973</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing E634</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R36223</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">15619451</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A39314)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 104194)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1591:66)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A testimony wherein is shewed certain weighty reasons why the national ministers, their way and practice, is conscientiously disowned, and their maintenance by tythes or other hire denyed also, a testimony, from a certain experience, to the people called Presbyterians, and all that are zealous in their way : also, a testimony to them called Anabaptists, with some reflections upon a book (propogated among them), called The child's instructor, .../ by a sufferer for the testimony of truth against deceit, and the antichristian oppression of tythes ... Sebastion Ellythorp.</title>
                  <author>Ellythorp, Sebastian, d. 1695.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>31 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed and sold by T. Sowle ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1692.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="personal_name">Keach, Benjamin, 1640-1704. --  Child's instructor.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Tithes --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Society of Friends --  Apologetic works.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Presbyterians --  Controversial literature.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Anabaptists --  Controversial literature.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-04 </date>
            <label>Simon Charles </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-04 </date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:104194:1"/>
            <p>A TESTIMONY Wherein is Shewed Certain Weighty REASONS Why the National Ministers, their Way and Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice is Conscientiously disowned, and their Maintenance by <hi>Tythes</hi> or other Hire Denyed. ALSO, A Testimony, from a certain Experience, to the People called <hi>Presbyterians,</hi> and all that are zealous in their way. ALSO, A Testimony to them called <hi>Anabaptists;</hi> with some Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flections upon a Book (propagated among them) called, <hi>The Child's Instructor,</hi> wherein the Author hath vented many De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tractions and Slanders against the <hi>Light within,</hi> and the People that bear Testimony of it. Which herein are plainly answer'd, and the true Light and Way of Life, in which the Antient <hi>Christians</hi> walked, and of which they testified, and which is now the same, is faithfully Vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated.</p>
            <q>
               <p>By a Sufferer in Bonds for the Testimony of Truth against Deceit, and the Antichristian Oppression of Tythes, and other forced Maintenance for the Ministry, Imposition of Oaths, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <bibl>Sebastian Ellythorp.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed, and Sold by <hi>T. Sowle</hi> at the <hi>Crooked-Billet,</hi> in <hi>Holywell-Lane,</hi> in <hi>Shoreditch,</hi> 1692.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:104194:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:104194:2"/>
            <div type="testimony">
               <head>A Testimony, wherein is shewed certain weighty Reasons why the National Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisters, their Way and Practice is Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scientiously disown'd, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Kind Friends and Neighbours;</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>FOrasmuch as I am sensible that some of you may have thoughts in your minds, what may be the cause wherefore I chuse rather to expose my self and Family to great Losses and Inconveniency, then conform to the National way of Worship, but more especially now when there is some Indulgence as to the point of Conformity; yet I come under the like Sufferings, rather than pay what hath been long accustomed to the National Ministry, or Teachers; and whether I may have a sufficient Reason for my so doing; for as to what my Adversary the Priest, or some rash people have cast upon me, as Wilfulness, and Stubbornness, or Covetous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness for saving my Money, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I hope that you all who have known my Conversation for some Years, may have observed that I have not shewed my self a wilful, stubborn or contentious person in other matters; and as for saving my Money by with-holding what my Adversary demands, I doubt not but that you are sensible that I have suffered, and am yet liable to suffer on this account, much more then the <hi>payment</hi> of all these things would be; which consider'd, there is ground to conclude that my former and present Sufferings for this cause are either very foolish, or truly Conscientious.</p>
               <p>Therefore for the satisfaction of my Neighbours, and all moderate and sober people where this may come, I do declare, that I had my Education according to the strictest sort of the National Worship, as it was in that time; and in my young years it pleased God to stir me up, with the most diligent Enquirers, to seek after the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of him, and Salvation by Jesus Christ, and by the space of ten Years I bestowed no small labour in travelling, hearing, writing, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:104194:3"/> to gain what knowledge was possible for me to attain unto, by dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent following such as were accounted the most eminent Teachers in those dayes, and many times with earnest desire, and much zeal towards God, and a great treasure of mens Opinions I then gather<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed into Notion and Writing; But all that did not minister satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction and comfort to my Soul, for there was a secret Witness in my Conscience which did testifie, that the ground of separation from God (<hi>viz.</hi> Sin and Transgression) did yet stand in dominion in me, and in the sence of this I passed many a sorrowful hour in secret.</p>
               <p>Then when the highest Notionists in all Professions fail'd, the Lord God in his tender Mercy having visited the Souls of some, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealing his Son Christ Jesus, the Light of the World, whom he hath given and appointed (as was declared by his Servants of old) a Witness to the People, and a Leader and Commander to all that receive, and truly follow him, the Author of Eternal Salvation to all that obey him; these he sent forth in the Power of his Spirit, to preach him and Reconciliation to God, and Salvation in him to as many as should hear his Voice, turn at his Reproof, and in true self-denyal become followers of him in the day of their Visitation, in the receiving of which Testimony, through God's mercy, I came to see the Mysteries of his Kingdom opened, and my mind being turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed inward, the true Shepherd's Voice I came to hear, and his leading forth of the ways of Death and Destruction, into the way of Life and Peace; and this Christ Jesus that Prophet, whom God hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed that all should hear, the same that was born Testimony of by the Prophet, Apostles, and true Christians in the Primitive times, whom God hath sent to bless his People, <hi>in turning every one of them from their Iniquities,</hi> Acts 3.22,26. And then I came clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to see that all who had taken upon them in mans will, and for worldly Honour and Gain, to be Expounders of Scripture, and Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers and Instructers of people concerning the things of God, were all blind Guides, false Teachers, and Ministers of Satan, and in the same ground which the false Prophets of old, of whom the Lord said, <hi>They ran and he never sent them, and therefore they did not profit the People at all, being indeed such as feed themselves, but let the Flock be scat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered;</hi> read <hi>Jer.</hi> 23. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 13. &amp; Chap. 34. And the Apostle <hi>Peter,</hi> in 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.1. plainly foretold, that as there was false Prophets among the People in former dayes, so there should be false Teachers among <hi>professing Christians;</hi> and in the third Verse he describes them, that
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:104194:3"/>
                  <hi>through. Covetousness with feigned Words they should make Merchandize of People,</hi> &amp;c. And now that this is an evident mark of the Priests of this Generation, all whose understandings God hath opened, may clearly see, and I do surely believe (that according to Scripture-Testimony) Christ Jesus is the same, yesterday, to day, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever; and the Way, Truth and Worship of God hath never chang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed since the Apostles dayes, though unstable deceitful men have been continually changing, as worldly advantages have appeared, that hath always drawn them.</p>
               <p>And now its very evident that the National Ministers and Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers whom great multitudes follow (for they being of the world, the world heareth them, 1 <hi>John</hi> 4.5.) they clearly differ from the true Ministers and Preachers of the Gospel in the Primitive times (as appears by Scripture-Testimony) in many particulars.</p>
               <p n="1">As, 1<hi>st,</hi> They differ in their Call and Ordination; for the true Ministers and Teachers in the Apostles days, they were fitted and called to that Work and Service by the Holy Ghost, <hi>Acts</hi> 13.2,4. And where mention is made of some being chosen by the Church, and laying on of hands, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> the Scripture plainly testifies, that <hi>such were to be of Honest Report, Blameless men, and full of the Holy Ghost,</hi> Acts 6.3. 1 Tim. 3. And we cannot find in Scripture, that in the true Church they did at any time chuse men for their being learned in <hi>Heathenish</hi> Books and Languages, or that any proud, covetous, drunken, vicious, prophane men were ever chosen or appointed (by them) to that Work: But it is well known that in this Generation men put their Children to Universities as to get a Trade, with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect to Preferment, ease, &amp; Worldly Gain thereby; and when they have gotten their degrees of Natural Learning, then they are set up by People to be Teachers, be they never so vicious, ungodly and prophane, such as God never appointed to that Work in any Age or Generation.</p>
               <p n="2">2<hi>dly,</hi> They differ in their Practice; the true Ministers in the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive times they spake and preached as the Spirit gave them utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, and that which they had seen, heard &amp; handled of the Word of Life, that they declared; they Prayed and Sung with the Spirit, and with Understanding; they sought not peoples worldly Estates to themselves, but to bring People to God; we read not any where in Scripture that they had their Prayers set down in a Book for all seasons and occasions; nor that they preached by Books; nor that they sung (and gave People to sing) <hi>David's</hi> Words turn'd into
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:104194:4"/> Rhimes; nor that they sprinkled Infants, and called it the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Baptism; nor that they gave people Bread and Wine, and called it the Sacrament of the Body and Blood of Christ; nor that they Married people for Money, nor Buried people for Money, nor that they Excommunicated people for not conforming to such things. Much might be written, wherein they differ in Practice from the Antient <hi>Christians,</hi> as recorded in the Scriptures, but this in brief.</p>
               <p n="3">3<hi>dly,</hi> They differ in their Maintenance; Christ sent forth his Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters with this Command, <hi>Freely have ye received, freely give, or minister:</hi> And all their Allowance we read of, was into whatsoever House they entred and were received, there to eat such things as were set before them: And we can find no Scripture-Record that ever any of Christ's Ministers either received or demanded <hi>Tythes,</hi> or any other settled or forced Maintenance, or that they sued or imprisoned any for with-holding from them part of the increase of their Labours, Grounds, or Cattel, or Money for Offerings, Smoke, Plough, Geese, Hens, or Bees, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But <hi>Paul,</hi> who was a true Minister of Christ, and travelled, preached, and laboured much more then any of these; he wrought with his Hands, rather then he would be chargeable to any; and what he did receive for supply of his Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessities, in his great Travels and Sufferings, in Prisons, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> it was the free Gift of such as were converted to God by their Ministry, and not desired by him upon his own account, but theirs, <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.17. And,</p>
               <p n="4">4<hi>thly,</hi> They differ in Doctorine: we read in Scripture that Christ's Ministers being sent of him, they went forth and preached that men should Repent, and that they should bring forth Fruits meet for Repentance, <hi>Mark</hi> 6.12. <hi>Acts</hi> 26.20. and that <hi>Christians</hi> should not let Sin reign in their mortal Bodies, nor obey it in the Lust thereof, neither yield their Members as Instruments of Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteousness unto Sin, but of Righteousness to God, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.12,13. But the Teachers of this Generation, who profess to be the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters of Christ and the Gospel; though they sometimes talk of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, sorrow for Sin, Contrition, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> yet they say, <hi>That men cannot but commit Sin while they live, and it will prevail in their Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers daily, while they are on this side the Grave.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And the most Barbarous and Atheistical people upon Earth can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not commit Sin here no longer then they live, for in the Grave none can either commit Sin, nor repent from Sin: And Christ Jesus
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:104194:4"/> testifieth, that <hi>They who dye in their Sins, where he is they cannot come,</hi> John 8.21. Again,</p>
               <p>The true Ministers <hi>were sent to turn People from Darkness to Light, and from Satan's Power to God,</hi> Acts 26.18. But these turn People from one Tradition and Formal Observation to another, which they change and alter as opportunities appear for their advantage in this World. Again,</p>
               <p>The true Ministers preached among the <hi>Gentiles, The Son of God revealed in them,</hi> and this Mystery, <hi>Christ in them the Hope of Glory, warning and teaching every man,</hi> that <hi>they might present every man per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect in Christ Jesus,</hi> Gal. 1.16. Coll. 1.27,28.</p>
               <p>But the Money-seeking-Ministers, oppose this Doctrine, and many of them make a mock at Christ within, and Light within, and at Gods Work being perfected in any while they live upon Earth; and they teach People to hear them talk of Mans notions of things without them, whereby their Hearts are not at all bettered as to their own inward states and conditions. Again, The true Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters Preach'd, that as many as are led by the Spirit of God, are the Sons or Children of God, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.14.</p>
               <p>But the other teach People, that as many as have Water sprin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kled on their Faces by them, (which they call <hi>Baptism</hi>) are thereby made Children of God, Members of Christ and Inheriters of the Kingdom of Heaven, witness their <hi>Catechism.</hi> And tho the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture plainly testify, <hi>that the Ʋnrighteous shall not Inherit the Kingdom of God, or of Heaven,</hi> 1 Cor. 6.9,10. Gal. 5.21. And the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postle cautions People <hi>that they be not deceived, for neither Fornicators, nor Idolaters, nor Adulterers, nor Effeminate,</hi> (Wanton or Unclean Persons) <hi>nor Thieves, nor Covetous, nor Drunkards, nor Revilers, nor Extortioners shall Inherit the Kingdom of God.</hi> And its very evident that some (if not many) that are so Sprinkled by the Priests when they are Children, and also Catechized and Taught by them after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, and yet are doers of such things as are there mentioned, to exclude out of Gods Kingdom. Again, Christ Jesus, the faithful and true Witness, said, <hi>The Hour is coming, in which all that are in the Graves shall hear his Voice, and shall come forth, they that have done good to the Resurrection of Life, and they that have done Evil to the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surrection of Damnation,</hi> 1 Joh. 5,28.29.</p>
               <p>But the Parish-Priests, when any person is Buried, for whom they can get Fees, they say, <hi>We commit the Body of this our dear Brother to the Ground, in sure and certain hope of Resurrection to Eternal Life:</hi>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:104194:5"/> And this they say without any enquiry, or consideration, whether they have done good or evil; and very many People being wholly given up to believe whatever they say, are thereby setled in a groundless security, and vain hope, not searching the Scriptures, nor considering that every one must receive a righteous Recompence of Reward from the Hand of the just God, according to their Works, and that there is no respect of persons with him. So now it is very evident to every one who shall in the Fear of God, singly observes the Testimony of Scripture, concerning the Doctrine of Christ and his Apostles, and true Ministers therein recorded, and compare the same with the Doctrine of the Ministers and Preachers of this Generation, who Preach for Tythes, and great sums of Money, and so live in Pride and Voluptuousness, who have a long time striven to force their Doctrine and Way of Worship upon all People, however with Cruelty and Violence to exact unjust and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reasonable payment for it, even from them that cannot receive it, hereby it will plainly appear that their Work runs even paralel with the false Prophets of old, and theirs of whom the Lord said, <hi>They strengthen the Hands of the Wicked, that he should not return from his wicked way, by promising him Life,</hi> Ezek. 13.22.</p>
               <p>These are but a few things of many that are clearly seen and opened by the Spirit of the Lord, which is the same now in all that wait to be led and instructed by it, as in former Generations, and is freely given of God even to the simple among Men, who in true fear wait to receive its Testimony, which is against Sin and Iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and all Deceit in every Heart, and against every evil way and work; and the reproof thereof being received and self-denied, and the evil turned from, and Sin forsaken, then the same Spirit that Convinces of Sin, and Condemns all Unrighteousness, as the mind comes to be turned to it and exercised in it, by it the under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing is truely opened, and the way of Life and Peace, and Salvation in Christ Jesus revealed; and therein watching and abid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in him, and not to return to folly, nor to any enticing Vanity, or allurment in this World, nor to deny him before Men, tho' called to suffer for the Testimony of him, and of his Name and Truth, and spiritual Worship, which hath been the lot of his faithful Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesses, and true Followers throughout Ages and Generations: And this observe, if we read the Scriptures through, and the most cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dible Histories extant, from <hi>Cain</hi> and <hi>Able</hi> to this day, we may find that it hath never been any long time together wherein the true
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:104194:5"/> Innocent Servants of God have not been exercised in Afflictions, and suffering Persecution, and many times by the means of such as made the highest Profession and shew of Religion, as the Priests and false Prophets, who were in greatest favour with Kings and Rulers, raised the most Persecution, as against <hi>Micaiah, Jeremiah,</hi> and <hi>Amos,</hi> by whose means they were threatned, imprisoned, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> under the false charges of Evil speaking, Conspiring, false Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecy, and seeking peoples hurt: Who but the <hi>Scribes, Pharisees, Chief Priests</hi> and <hi>Counsellors,</hi> persecuted to death the Son of God, imprisoned the Apostles, stoned <hi>Stephen,</hi> and raised Persecution against <hi>Paul</hi> and others, and among such as have had the Name of <hi>Christians, Bishops, Doctors, Priests,</hi> and high Learned men, have been the chief Agents in <hi>burning, torturing, imprisoning,</hi> and spoil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Lord's tender people in <hi>England,</hi> and elsewhere, both formerly and of late Years.</p>
               <p>So now in true Sobriety, in the Fear of God seriously consider, (these things being made manifest, and clearly opened to my un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstanding by the Spirit of the Lord, and I being surely perswa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded of the truth thereof.) Whether now I have not sufficient ground to separate from these Teachers, and all their invented Formalities, and to prize the Lord's Mercy in discovering their Deceits, and also to with-hold all assistance from them in that work of deceiving others, of whose destruction I should not be clear if (knowingly) I should maintain, assist, or strengthen the Hands of the great Deceivers, Servants and Instruments in that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicious work.</p>
               <p>And now dear People, all who may be herein concerned, who have hitherto been Followers of these Men, to your serious and sober Consideration these few particulars following are proposed, <hi>Viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>First,</hi> Whether ye do not believe that the Eternal State of your Souls, that is everlasting Blessedness or Misery, is a matter of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern to every one, more weighty then any thing in this World?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> Whether ye do not believe that the everlasting Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or Damnation of every man and woman's Soul doth depend on their laying hold of, and closing with the Mercy of God in the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:104194:6"/> Lord Jesus Christ, and their believing on him, and faithful follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and abiding in him, or their sleighting, rejecting, and turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing away from him, in the day of their Visitation?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Whether the day of every ones Visitation, wherein it may be possible for them to work out their Salvation, and to make their Calling and Election sure, can extend any further then the time of this short and uncertain Life?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fourthly,</hi> Whether ye would be content to trust the Evidences and assurance of your whole Estates in this World, in the hands of any Stranger that should offer to procure and keep them for you, for a certain sum of Money, and you, your Families and Posterity to depend and rely only upon his Words for all? or would you not think it necessary for you surely to know, receive, and have the keeping of them your selves?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fifthly,</hi> Whether now in this the Day of your Visitation, every one of you have not absolute need to wait on God, that he may open your understandings, and give you to know the mystery of Salvation in Christ Jesus, every one for your selves; and that you may every one Pray for your selves, and feel access to God in the Spirit for your selves, and know true Repentance and Faith given you of God, and wrought by his Spirit and Power in your selves, and to know a growth in Grace in your selves, and every one to be inwardly exercised by God's Spirit in your selves, to feel and truly to know these things, and no longer to rely and wholly to depend on a vain, proud, or covetous man, or any Hireling and self-ended man, to know for you, understand for you, pray for you, search the Scriptures for you, and believe for you, while ye live at ease in Ignorance, and count that most weighty matter, the eternal state of your immortal Souls to be of so little value, as wholly to trust him with it, and to take all on his Word till Death come; and then if it prove so, that these men be indeed Deceivers, for geting Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney and worldly Gain, then your loss will be unrecoverable, and there can be no remedy for you?</p>
               <p>And now <hi>my Friends</hi> and <hi>Country People,</hi> and whom it may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern, where-ever this may come, To him that knows the secrets of
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:104194:6"/> all hearts I do appeal, that I have no end to my self in giving forth this Testimony, neither is it in Wrath and Revenge against that deceitful man, by whose Cruelty and continued Malice I have long suffered, and do suffer, nor against the Persons of any of that sort; for I am very sensible that after a little time we must all come to Judgment, and every one receive of the Just and Righteous God a full Reward according to our Works; and I being in the will of God brought into this exercise, which I could not with a clear Conscience avoid, and finding Peace and Acceptance with God therein, it came into my heart to give forth this plain and true Testi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony, to pass among my Neighbours and others, as way shall be made, that all such may be informed concerning the weighty Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons of my submitting to this Suffering, and enduring this Affliction, <hi>viz.</hi> To be separated from my Wife and Children, Kindred and Acquaintance, and from my earthly Habitation and Estate, and now in my Old Age to be shut up amongst hainous Transgressors, poor and destitute (and which is worse) wicked and prophane Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons; and all this without any necessity or cause, but to keep my Conscience void of offence to God, who hath certainly called me (and many more) to come out of <hi>Babylon,</hi> the false Spirit, the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of Harlots and Abominations of the Earth, in whose Skirts is found the Blood of the Saints and Martyrs of Jesus, by whose Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceries all Nations have been deceived; read <hi>Rev.</hi> 17. and 18. Chap. <hi>John</hi> saw in the Spirit that such a Mystery of Iniquity, Whore, False Spirit, False Church, should come up, <hi>By which Kindreds, Nations, Peoples and Tongues should be betwitched with her Sorceries, and made drunk with the Wine of her Fornication:</hi> And now it is very clear, that all the invented Forms and Ways of Worship that have been set up and agreed by mens Devices, and forced upon People since the Apostles dayes, hath all been in another Spirit then they were led by, and walked in, and for other ends then they sought after, who were the true Ministers &amp; Servants of our <hi>Lord Jesus Christ.</hi> And now my Soul is witness, (with many others) that now the Everlasting Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spel is Preached to them that dwell on the Earth, and to every People and Tongue, wherein the Call is, <hi>to Fear God, and to Worship him,</hi> Rev. 14.6,7. And now the false Teachers and Merchants of <hi>Babylon,</hi> that have been made rich by her Sorceries, and have made Merchandize of Bodies and Souls of men, <hi>Rev.</hi> 18.13. they are the great Opposers, and by Contention, Slanders, and all their cunning Craftiness en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:104194:7"/> to pervert the minds of People, and to keep them still in Ignorance of the Work of God's Spirit &amp; Power in themselves, that so they may yet make a prey of them, and when they can no longer therewith prevail, they have raised all the Persecution they have been able, and yet do to the utmost of their power; and this hath been a sure mark of Deceivers and false Worshippers throughout all Generations from <hi>Cain</hi> to this day, Cruelty, Force and Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence; But the true Worshippers, Servants and Ministers of God, and the Lord Jesus Christ, were never found in that work, as the Scripture very fully declares, 1 <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.29. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8,9.</p>
               <p>And now if any think or say, <hi>It seems strange that now when I am grown Old, and God hath given me Wife and Children, a considerable Habitation and Estate in the world, why now I cannot be satisfied to conform to the National Practice, and Laws, at least to pay the Priest, or cause, or suffer it to be done, (though I like not their doings, nor approve their practice) which many worldly Wise men do, and chuse to do to enjoy their Liberty and Estates, and avoid Sufferings?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Well Friends, search the Scriptures, and ye may find that Gods faithful Servants have been like-minded in former dayes, <hi>Shadrach, Meshach</hi> and <hi>Abednego</hi> were prefered in the Province of <hi>Babylon,</hi> and were esteemed Wise men, yet they refused to do as other Wise men did; for its said, That the Judges, Counsellors, and all the Principal Men of the Kingdom submitted to the King's decree; yet they boldly refused, though the Penalty was to be cast into the Burning Fiery Furnace. And <hi>Daniel,</hi> a man greatly preferred to a state of living honourably in the World, and though Princes and People obeyed that Decree of King <hi>Darius,</hi> yet <hi>Daniel</hi> rather submitted to be cast into the Lyons Den, then to dispence with the exercise of his Conscience towards God: And the Apostle <hi>Paul</hi> in his day and time was of the same mind, that what he was perswaded in his own Heart he ought to do in obedience to God, his nearest Friends could not diswade him from, though he fore-saw great Sufferings should attend him therein, <hi>Acts</hi> 21.13. So now it is with me, and others like-minded, but as it hath been with the Lord's faithful Servants in former dayes.</p>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:104194:7"/>
               <p>And now my beloved Country-men, and all who are sober minded, in whom there is any tender Desires towards God, The cause of my present Writing, is my earnest desire for you that ye may no longer be beguiled by self-ended, and deceitful men in this most weighty matter relating to the eternal state of your Souls; But that you may all retire inward, and encline your Ear to him, whom God hath given for a Witness to the People, who sheweth unto man his Way, and declares to him the Thoughts of his Heart, who convinces the World of Sn, turns from Iniquity, and leads into all Truth; even Christ Jesus, in whom alone is Salvation, who is the Author of it to all that obey him, yea, he is to be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beyed who calls out of Sin, and from every sinful way and work; for while men live in Sin, and continue Workers of Iniquity, the Seperation from God remains, and all Pretences of Religion, and Worship is in vain, as is fully declared in Scripture, <hi>Isa.</hi> 1.11. <hi>&amp;c. John</hi> 9.31. <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.22,23, And Christ Jesus in his Spiritual Mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>festation, to all that receive and truely follow him, is the same in these dayes, as in former Generations, And that ye may all come truely to know him, and his saving work in every one of your Souls, now in this the day of your Visitation, and that none of you may miss, or come short of it, is the real and Hearty desire of your Friend, and truely Well-Wisher,</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Sebastian Ellythorp.</signed>
                  <dateline>From the Place of my Confinement in <hi>York</hi> Castle, <date>the 3<hi>d Day</hi> of the 5<hi>th Month,</hi> 1691.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="testimony">
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:104194:8"/>
               <head>To them called <hi>Presbyterians.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>NOw ye my beloved Friends, Neighbours and Country-People, in whom there hath been raised some desires towards God and the knowledge of his Way, whereby you have been stirred up to seek further then the common sort who sit down at ease, contenting themselves with any dark shew of Worship which Men in their wills set up, and their Teachers for profit and wordly advantage observe and practice, and your Eyes being a little opened to see their deadness, coldness, formality, and earthly-mindedness, a secret convincement hath been raised in your understandings, that this is not the ancient Path, and Way in which the Apostles and true Christians walked in the Primitive times, nor in which the Zealous People of God (who suffered for their Testimony) walked in after Generations; and upon these considerations, some stirrings have risen in you to seek and enquire further, and then you not under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing the weight of that Heavenly Testimony of our Lord Jesus, <hi>Luk.</hi> 17.20,21,23,24. <hi>You not knowing that the Kingdom of God comes not with observation, as lo here, and lo there, but is within you:</hi> Men have called unto you, saying, <hi>See here,</hi> and <hi>Se there</hi> and you (contrary to the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sel, and command of our Lord Jesus) have gone after them, and great multitudes have been drawn (most especially in a time of outward Liberty) into that called the <hi>Presbyterian</hi> way, and their Teachers have appeared to them in a more refined sort of Prayers and preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing then the other, (<hi>viz.</hi> the common sort) and with some higher Notions, and more shew of Zeal, and they cuningly gloss their own Tenents, and Practices, and reproach, and bitterly inveigh against others, and some of you travel far, and are become eager followers of them, and peradventure now hope you are right, and that you have found the way, and need seek no further.</p>
               <p>Well Friends, where you now are, I was, many years ago: I have trodden the same path, I diligently sought and enquird among them, and have large experience of what is there to be found, I have seen and tasted both their Root and Fruit, and well know it to be out of the same Ground, and of the same kind with the common
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:104194:8"/> sort, onely a little more finely glossed in shew and appearance; and in this as well as the other form of Profes<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>, people are brought no further then to rely upon men, and to depend on them for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinual direction, in their Knowledge, Belief and Practice in all matters of Religion and Worship; and these Teachers whom you follow, differ not in the ground from these you have left, for their fitting for their Ministry, is by Schools and Colledges, where they also learn <hi>Heathenish Books,</hi> whereby to attain to the Knowledge of Languages, which is but natural; and the Scripture saith, <hi>the natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral man understands not the things that be of God, nor can he know them, because they are spiritually discerned;</hi> and the motives that draws them to their Ministry, is that thereby they may be highly esteemed among Men, and called <hi>Masters,</hi> and get <hi>Money,</hi> and Worldly Riches; and I well know that when they were upermost in this Nation, they were as <hi>Ambitious, Coveteous, Contentious</hi> and <hi>Cruel,</hi> and sought as much after the greatest Livings, <hi>Tythes,</hi> and all other Forced Maintenance, and many of them as <hi>bitter Persecutors</hi> as the Bishops have been since; for in the dayes of Parliment and Protector, if any had but offered to Query of them or dispute in their Assemblies (as <hi>Paul's</hi> manner was, <hi>Asts</hi> 17.2.) then they had a <hi>Popish Law,</hi> which was made in Queen <hi>Mary's</hi> time, to defend their <hi>Popish Priests,</hi> and by it the <hi>Presbyterian Priests</hi> caused Men or Women to be Imprisoned, and many have suffered much upon that account; and in that time I saw a Petition drawn up and signed by very many of that sort of <hi>Priests,</hi> requesting the Parliament, to establish some Law for restraining <hi>Anabaptists, Antinomians, Seekers,</hi> and others who shrouded themselves (as they said) under Churches Independent, seperate Congregations, and Liberty of Conscience, pressing them much to suppress all others, and to establish their form; and some of them sought to draw other People to joyn with them there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, to stir up Persecution: so whatever they smoothly pretend to, now that they have been a while under; when they had Worldly Power on their side, they were as Riged, for Publick Places, Forced Maintenance, and Cruel Persecution upon all accounts, as ever any <hi>Protestants</hi> were; and their Brethren in <hi>New-England</hi> caused many of the Lords tender Servants to be cruelly Imprisoned, &amp; Spoiled, some they Whipt, some they Branded with hot Irons, some they Cut of Ears, others they Banished, and four they put to Death, and all for no other cause but the exercise of their Consciences towards God, and
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:104194:9"/> their faithful holding the Testimony they had received of him; and one of their chief Priests put forth a Book to excuse their Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and other Cruelties: And as to their Practice in their Worship, tho they seem a little more refin'd in their formal Observations then some others, as Praying without Book, expounding, sprink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Infants without Cross or Sureties, Marrying without Ring, and leaving out some dark Formalities in Burying their Dead, and lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing aside the old Catechism, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Yet they do all these things for the same ends <hi>viz.</hi> For Money, and filthy Lucre; and as to their Doctrine, its in most things the same, as denying the Light of Christ, (or however the sufficiency of it,) and the teaching of his Spirit, holding the ceasing of Divine Revelation, necessity of Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing during Life, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Except they differ from some others, in hold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Election</hi> and <hi>Reprobation</hi> of Persons in Gods eternal Decree, which Doctrine if true, they and all others may cease Preaching, Praying, and all other Religious Exercises, for not any thing that they, or any Men can do, can in any wise alter Gods Decree; But I have heard some argue thus, that as God hath decreed the end, so also he hath Decreed the means, tending thereto: So that whom he hath ordained to Salvation, he hath also ordained, that they shall be Baptized, read, hear them Preach, believe their Doctrine, receive their Sacrament diligently, observe Ordinances, come into and continue in Church-fellowship, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And with whom they (through their cunning craftiness) thus prevail, they perswade to continue trading with them, to buy their Merchandize, to receive and believe their Meanings of the Scriptures, and their Consequences therefrom, and their Doctrines and Conclusions to take on their word, and all their days to continue learning of them, and giving them large Wages besides. But to this I Answer, that by this Doctrine they would bring in abundance of unclean, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sanctified <hi>Christians,</hi> Believers, and Church-Members, as they call them, whom they have gathered, instructed, and led in the belief and practice of their Profession and Way, who yet (with themselves) remain Workers of Iniquity, such as the pure holy and Righteous God never own'd, nor accepted, and such as the Scriptures plainly declare, shall not be received, but shut out of Gods Kingdom, <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.21.23. <hi>Luk.</hi> 13.27,28. <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.8.</p>
               <p>And this Doctrine of theirs, also excludes multitudes of People, to whom they have never travelled to preach that they call the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:104194:9"/> Gospel, nor their <hi>Baptism, Sacraments</hi> and <hi>Ordinances,</hi> who were never instructed in their Belief and Church-Fellowship, yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding in Temperance, Chastity, Sobriety, Honesty, Humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, bearing and forgiving Injuries, and other <hi>Christian</hi> Vertues, which God ever owned and approved, far exceed many of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessed <hi>Christians,</hi> and their Teachers too; for tho the Clergy-Men of all sorts (that I know) have pretended to derive their Commission from Christ's Words to his Disciples, <hi>Go reach all Nations, Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizing them,</hi> &amp;c. yet they usually travel no farther to Teach and Baptize, then the first great <hi>Tythe-Parish,</hi> or Rich Living that they can obtain, and there they mostly live at ease, in Pride and Fulness, and takes no care what becomes of other Nations; yet I do believe that God who is no respecter of persons, but in every Nation ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepteth them that fear him, and work Righteousness, hath not alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether slighted the Nations far remote, (who are counted Heathens and Infidels, by the nominal Christians) nor left them utterly desti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute of the means of Salvation, in and by the Lord Jesus Christ, whom he hath given and appointed a Light to the Gentiles, and to be his Salvation to the Ends of the Earth, and that the great Heart-Searcher, may sometimes find more Faith, and good <hi>Fruit,</hi> in and among some of them, then among many great Professors of Christianity, as the Scripture declares of <hi>Job, Elihu, Cornelius,</hi> and the <hi>Centurion</hi> mentioned, <hi>Mat.</hi> 8.10. and divers others in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Generations, who had not the Law and Ordinances in the Letter, as <hi>Israel</hi> had, and yet had received the knowledge of God, and his works in them, and shewed the work of the Law written in their Hearts; and God himself Testified of <hi>Job,</hi> that there was none like him in the Earth, a perfect and upright Man, that feared God and eschewed evil, and therein he was accepted of God, when ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, that had the Law and Testimony and Ordinances in the Letter, and these advantages, yet taking Liberty to live in Sin, and Iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Transgression of the Law, were therefore rejected as the Scriptures abundantly Testifie, and as to Gods fore-Knowledge of all things, that is a Secret, and Secret things belongs to God; but things that are revealed, to us and to our Children for ever, <hi>Deut.</hi> 29.29. And he hath revealed that his Will is, that all Men should be saved, and come to the Knowledge of the Truth, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.4. And that the wicked should forsake his way, and the unrighteous Man <gap reason="missing" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ pages">
                     <desc>〈1+ pages missing〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="testimony">
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:104194:10"/>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="missing" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ pages">
                     <desc>〈1+ pages missing〉</desc>
                  </gap> of our Lord Jesus Christ, as the God of Mercy, who is no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>specter of Persons, who would have all men to be saved, hath universally extended the same unto all, that all men through him might believe; for I have observed in a little Book, called or tituled, <hi>The Child's Instructor,</hi> set forth by one of your Profession (named <hi>B. Keech</hi>) and exposed in Print to publick view, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in after a deal of Verses and flourishing Notions, the said Author undertakes to declare his Opinion and Judgment concerning the Light within; and saith, <hi>Because there is a sort of People risen up of late dayes, that say there is a Light within them, and every one that cometh into the World, which if walked up to, will teach them all things necessary to Salvation: But,</hi> saith he, <hi>I shall shew that they do err exceedingly, not knowing, nor believing the Scriptures,</hi> &amp;c. I answer, That forasmuch as the Lord in mercy hath visited my Soul, in causing his Light to shine out of Darkness, which hath shined in my Heart, to give the Knowledge of him in the face of Jesus Christ. I acknowledge my self to be one of these people, whom this Author is pleased to charge with vile and pernicious Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, Error, cursed Doctrine, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And for his affirming that <hi>we know not, nor believe the Scriptures:</hi> That is no less then a bold and impudent Lye; for we have all the means of knowing the Scriptures that he has, as natural men, and many of us have been diligent improvers of the same in our day, but more especially by the shinings in of the Light, or manifestation of the Spirit of Christ in our Hearts, we are confirmed in a certain belief of what is therein declared, and the Testimony that we have born of late dayes, concerning the Light; hath been the same, and no other' then the faithful Followers of him did formerly bear, as is fully and largely declared in the Scriptures of Truth, <hi>viz.</hi> That Christ the true Light lighteth every man that comes into the World; and that he that follows him shall not abide in Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, but have the Light of Life; and the same that gives Light to them that sit in Darkness; guides in the Way of Peace, <hi>John</hi> 1.9. <hi>John</hi> 8.12. <hi>Luk.</hi> 1.79, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Then this Author says, <hi>he will shew what this Light is, and what it is not;</hi> and he saith, <hi>It is an excellent Spirit of Knowledge and Ʋnderstanding, that God hath given, placed, and formed in man, which is called the Candle of the Lord; together with the Law, or sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance of the first Covenant, written in the Hearts of the worst of men,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:104194:10"/> which</hi> (he saith) <hi>is much darkened in the Ʋnregenerate by the Fall and Transgression.</hi> Then he saith, <hi>This Light is not God, nor Christ the anointed of God, nor the Holy Spirit which flows from the Father and from Christ.</hi> Yet he saith, <hi>By this Light thou mayst understand that there is a God, or an eternal invisible Power which did create all things.</hi> 2dly, <hi>That he is the Soveraign Lord of the whole Creation, and doth preserve all things which he hath made, and that every thing is at his disposing.</hi> 3dly, <hi>It will teach thee that he ought to be Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shipped as the highest Beeing, and no other besides him.</hi> 4thly, <hi>It will Convince of Sin, and Reprove Wickedness, and shew Evil Thoughts.</hi> 5thly, <hi>It will teach Righteousness towards men, and to exercise a just Mind and Spirit in all thy Ways and Doings.</hi> 6thly, <hi>It will teach Humility and Loliness to render due Respects to all.</hi> 7thly, <hi>It will teach to do to all men as thou wouldst be done unto, and that in every thing.</hi> Which he largely expresseth in Particulars, wherein tho' I do not transcribe his Words at large, yet I take the Substance without any intended detraction from its true Sence.</p>
               <p>In Answer whereunto, I first observe, he holds that all things is, or may be done by something in man, as himself, a Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and as fallen man too, for (he saith) This Light and Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstanding is much darkened in the Unregenerate, by the Fall and Transgression. So we must understand that he intends Man in his natural Understanding and Abilities, yea, by his own Spirit and understanding in that state, without the shinings in of God, Christ, or the Holy Spirit which flows from the Father and from Christ, may know, understand, and be taught all these things. Surely this Author hath the most set up Man, as of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self, capable of Understanding, Knowledge, and attaining to Righteousness without the enlightning, teaching, and power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful working of God, Christ, or the holy Spirit in him, that ever I read, or heard of any <hi>Protestant</hi> in all my days; the Scripture saith, <hi>The World by Wisdom knows not God;</hi> and that men in their natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral state are Darkness, and understand not the things of God, nor can know them; because they are Spiritually discerned, and that it is God that searcheth the Hearts, and declareth unto man his Thoughts, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Yet this Author affirms, that man in his fallen and unregenerate state hath such an excellent Spirit in him, by which (though it be much darkened by the fall, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) he may understand, be taught, convinced and instructed in all these
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:104194:11"/> seven particulars (aforementioned.) Now let all the Wise in heart in the fear of God, judge how this man hath shewed his Knowledge or Belief of the Scriptures, or how the Scripture-Testimony concerning these things, and his Assertions can be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled.</p>
               <p>Then he saith, <hi>The Law given to</hi> Israel <hi>was a more glorious Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nistration then this in all men.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I Answer: That then thereby they should have come to higher Attainments then the seven particulars, which he hath affirmed may be attained to by the Light within, as concerning the Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of God, Righteousness, Justice, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Yet one of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets said of them who had this Law, <hi>That there was no Truth, Mercy nor Knowledge of God in the Land,</hi> Hos. 4.1. And much more of the like nature the Scriptures testifie concerning them. So it appears that notwithstanding the more glorious Ministration to them, (as he calls it) yet they were much short of these good Fruits and glorious Effects, which (as he confesseth) may be attained to by the Light within, where it is faithfully followed, obeyed, or lived up to: yet I fear that if a strict search be made among the great Professors of <hi>Christianity</hi> in this Age, and amongst those also of Profession with this Author, they may be found much short of the seven particulars by him mentioned, whereby it may appear that notwithstanding all their high Notions, whereby he so low esteemed the Light within, as darkened by the Fall, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> yet they do not live up thereto, no more then <hi>Israel</hi> did: But <hi>Simeon</hi> the just and devout man, upon whom the holy Ghost was, he more highly esteem'd the Light, whereby the <hi>Gentiles</hi> are lighted, then this Author, for he called it, <hi>The Glory of</hi> Israel, and that was no other then Christ, <hi>Luk.</hi> 2.30,31,32.</p>
               <p>But I observe, that when he hath thus far set up man in his attain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments without God, Christ or the holy Spirit, then he raises a fearful Accusation or Charge. (and that most wicked and notori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ously false) against us, for setting up an Inherent legal Righteous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness in man, denying the Righteousness of Christ and price of his precious Blood, holding that Christ fulfilled the Law for us no other way but as our Pattern, and this he calls <hi>a miserable Evil, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicious, Soul-destroying, cursed, and Popish Doctrine.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I Answer; Surely never a wicked, crafty and deceitful Thief shewed more subtilty, in crying, <hi>See there, turn Thief,</hi> pointing
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:104194:11"/> at some Innocent Person, that himself might escape undiscovered, then this deceitful man hath done; so that if Children and Young People, to whom he writes to abhor such Doctrine, come to a good understanding therof, they may see that it is his Doctrine that is to be abhorred, and not ours, as he wickedly hath insinuated; For we are so far from preaching, holding or believing any such Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, that we steadfastly believe and testifie, that notwithstand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that excellent Spirit which God hath formed in man, by which the things of man be known, yet the things of God no man knows but by the Spirit of God; and tho the Spirit of man be called the Candle of the Lord, yet it is Christ the true Light that lights it, and for that end that no man should put it under a Bushel, or under a Bed, but on a Candlestick, to shine forth in good Works, even in the sight of men; and for want of this faithful shining, or walking in the Light, the Candle of the Wicked is of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten put out. And tho this Author affirms, that <hi>men may be taught, and come to the knowledge of God, and of his Worship and righteous Ways,</hi> as is in the seven Particulars by him afore-mentioned, is expressed, <hi>by a Light that is not God, Christ, nor the holy Spirit:</hi> Yet we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve (according to Scripture-Testimony) <hi>that no man can know God the Father, but he to whom the Son reveals him,</hi> nor his Spiritual Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship, but by the <hi>teaching of his Spirit;</hi> and we believe that it is the holy Spirit that convinces the World of Sin, Righteousness and Judgment, and that of every Sin, which holy Spirit the uncircum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cised in Heart and Ears resist, as in former days, yet who do re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive it, and walk in it; the same Spirit that convinces of Sin, leads and guides into all Truth, and is the Comforter, and brings out of Condemnation, who come to be baptized with it, and therein buried with Christ, being crucified with him to the putting off the old man, as to the former Conversation, and puts on Christ the new and heavenly man, and as he is received so to walk in him; and herein is the Righteousness of the Law fulfilled in them that walk not after the Flesh, but after the Spirit; and this Righteous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness is not of man, nor wrought by the power or wisdom of man, but only of Christ, the Power and Wisdom of God, in them that truly believe, faithfully follow, and abide in him, and who come to be led by his Spirit, by which the things freely given us of God we truly know, and our receiving all of him: And this doth not detract from, nor make void the Righteousness and Sufferings of
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:104194:12"/> Christ, or shedding of his precious Blood, and giving his Life a Ransom, but which is the effect of the travail of his Soul, and that wherein the Father is glorified in all that hear his Voice, follow and abide in him, and bring forth the Fruits of his Spirit: And this Doctrine we have received, and do believe, and freely declare that all Men in their natural state, are gone out of the Way of Life; and Destruction and Misery are in their Wayes, and the Way of Peace (in that state) they cannot know; and that Christ Jesus the Light of the World, whom God the Father hath given a Light to lighten the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> and to be his Salvation to the ends of the Earth, is the Way, the Truth, and the Life, and that none can come to the Father but by him, and he is that Prophet of whom <hi>Moses</hi> spake, that all should hear, even in the Ministration and Testimony of his holy Spirit, whom God hath sent to bless his Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, in turning every one of them from their Iniquities. So what we hold and testifie concerning <hi>God, Christ,</hi> the <hi>Light,</hi> or <hi>holy Spirit,</hi> is the same Doctrine and no other then is fully and clearly held forth and testified of in the Scriptures; and if this Author cannot receive this Testimony, but will run into groundless Distinctions in the Imaginations of his carnal mind, being wise in his own Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit, and thereby seek to pervert the right Wayes of the Lord, and subvert the Souls of the Simple, by slandering the Innocent, we shall leave him and his Work to the Judgment of the great Day, but finds no cause to decline our faithful Testimony herein.</p>
               <p>But he is offended that any do affirm Christ to be within, saying, <hi>He is not to be believed that saith he is in the secret Chamber, the Heart.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I Answer: These words (the Heart) are by him added to Christ's Words, which bold attempt hath been accounted dangerous, <hi>Prov.</hi> 30.6. <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.18. And I do not find in all the Scriptures that any of the faithful Witnesses of Christ Jesus, have shut him out of the Heart; for how shall he search the Hearts if he be not there? And it is testified in <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.23. <hi>All the Churches shall know that I am he that searcheth the Reins and Hearts, and I will give unto every one of you according to your Works.</hi> And by this mans Assertion <hi>John</hi>'s Testimony herein was not to be believed, nor is not; so no won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that he slanders us, who dare contradict the plain Testimony of Scripture in so weighty a point, and indeed if he could exclude Christ out of peoples Hearts, the strong man Satan would reign there, and his Goods would be in peace. So here Children and
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:104194:12"/> Young People may see whose Seat and Kingdom this Author would have their Hearts to be, that would not have it believed that Christ is there.</p>
               <p>Then in another place he undertakes to inform his Readers of the insufficiency of the Light, <hi>viz.</hi> to shew (as he saith) what it cannot do, and saith, <hi>It cannot reveal Gospel-Mysteries, nor teach the Righteousness of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I Answer: We have sufficient ground to believe, that this man never made proof or tryal herein, that he never was a follower of the Light, or holy Spirit of Truth in its leadings, and yet dare be so bold as to accuse it of Insufficiency: For Christ saith, <hi>I am the Light of the World, he that follows me shall not abide in Darkness, but shall have the Light of Life;</hi> and that's a Gospel-Mystery. And the Apostle <hi>Paul</hi> who had more understanding of Gospel-Mysteries then this Author, witnessed it to be the shinings in of the Light of God in their Hearts, that gave the Knowledge of his Glory in the Face of Jesus Christ, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.6. And I do not find that ever any that received the Testimony of the true Light, and faithfully walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in it, did accuse it of Insufficiency: but the Murmurers and Complainers against the Light were such as walked after their own ungodly Lusts. And for the Scriptures, which he calls <hi>the more sure Word of Prophecy, to reveal the Lord Jesus Christ,</hi> &amp;c. I do af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm, that they who writ them, had the Gospel-Mysteries and Truths therein declared, revealed to and in them, by the Light or holy Spirit of Truth (which is one) before they spake or writ there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of; so thereby it was first revealed in them, before it was by them declared to others; since which time, and to this day many Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand of prophane Persons, and many worldly wise and learned men have had the Scriptures in the Letter, and some have been great Contenders about them, yet not receiving the same Spirit for their Guide, have been Strangers and Enemies to it, and to them that have walked in it, and were led by it, as this man hath largely ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifested himself; and if one Party may be taken for Evidence against another, very many and gross Errors do abound among the Nominal <hi>Christians,</hi> who all have the Scriptures, and make a great noise of Profession of them, and yet it is manifest by the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fusion and Contention that is amongst them; that as the Apostle said of the <hi>Jews, In reading</hi> Moses <hi>Writings the Vail is over their Hearts:</hi> which Vail was then taken away in turning to the Lord,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:104194:13"/> that Spirit which was and is a Gospel-Ministry, and was and is revealed by the Spirit of the Lord, and not by the bare Letter of the Scriptures without it.</p>
               <p>And where he saith, <hi>That the Law given to</hi> Israel, <hi>was a more glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Ministration then that in all men, which is that written in the Hearts,</hi> which he grants <hi>doth shew and teach the many good and weighty things aforementioned.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I Answer: This appears to be absolutely contrary to the Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stimony of Scripture, let the sober Reader seriously peruse 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.6. to the end of the Chapter, and <hi>Heb.</hi> 8.6. to the end: To which I refer.</p>
               <p>And for his charging the People that bear witness to the Light within, or manifestation of the Spirit, and the teachings of it, with <hi>denying the Imputed Righteousness of Christ, and the Vertue of his precious Blood, holding that Christ hath fulfilled the Law for us no other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise then as our Pattern, preaching Justification by the Works of the Law,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>These things I do declare to be absolute Slanders; for these Doctrines were never held nor preached by us: but yet I never read in Scripture, that the Apostles and true Ministers of Christ did Preach the <hi>imputed Righteousness of Christ,</hi> nor any Notions concerning the same for Justification to them that chose to live in Unrighteousness, for with this Doctrine multitudes of prophane, ignorant, and licentious people in <hi>Christendom,</hi> who have chosen to walk in the broad Way, have long flatter'd themselves, and one another: But I find that the Apostles and Primitive <hi>Christians</hi> were more serious, and looked for a nearer and more sure ground of Faith and Hope of the Salvation of their Souls, then the bare No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and Belief concerning what was long since done, suffered and fulfilled without them, so as to relie only thereupon for Justifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; and considering the Testimony of our Lord Jesus, <hi>That not every one that saith Lord, Lord, shall enter into the Kingdom of Heaven, but he that doth the Will of my Father which is in Heaven:</hi> and that <hi>many shall say in that day, Have we not Prophesied in thy Name,</hi> &amp;c. and yet shall be rejected, because <hi>workers of Iniquity,</hi> Matth. 7.21,22,23. And the Apostle <hi>John</hi> bears another sort of Testimony, to the little Children that he writ to, concerning this point, then this Author hath done to Children in this Age; 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.7,8,9,10. <hi>Little Children, let no man deceive you, he that doth Righteousness it Righteous
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:104194:13"/> even as he is Righteous; He that committeth Sin is of the Devil, and in this the Children of God are manifest, &amp; the Children of the Devil: He that doth not Righteousness is not of God,</hi> &amp;c. Which Testimony, and many more to the same purpose in the Scriptures, wherein is fully expressed the doing, working, and fulfilling of Righteousness (through the operation of the Spirit and Power of God) in all true Believers and Followers of the Lord Jesus Christ, are full as large and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>press to the point as the Doctrine of these People who believe in the Light, as by them held and preached, (clear from the false Representations, Perversions and Slanders of their Adversaries) which this Author hath exclaimed against with his <hi>Popish, cursed, pernicious, Soul-destroying,</hi> &amp;c. on purpose to scare Children and Young People there-from, as if the very hearing of Righteousness doing, working, or being fulfilled in them, by the working of the Spirit and Power of Christ in them, were the most dangerous Poyson they could possibly touch.</p>
               <p>And now if this Author be yet alive, I desire that he, and all other Broachers and Propagators of such Doctrine, (tending to the prejudicing and perverting the minds of Children and Young People in their tender Years, from receiving and closing with the Light of Christ, and working of his holy Spirit in them) may tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Repent of this their Wickedness, and retract this and all such their Books and Writings, least some thereby become hardned to their destruction, and their Blood be required at their Hands.</p>
               <p>And in true Humility, in the Fear of God I do admonish all Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents and Governors of Children, to beware how they suffer their Children to be leaven'd with Prejudice against the Light of Christ (in which they should believe, <hi>that they may be Children of Light,</hi> according to the Testimony of Jesus, <hi>John</hi> 12.36. By teaching, or causing, or suffering them to be taught in such corrupt Books, as this which this Author hath prepared (and hath been by him and others published with great applause) for their mis-information, as is largely made manifest.</p>
               <p>And now to him that surely understands the Secrets of all Hearts I am known, and to all that may see or hear this Testimony, I in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genuously declare, that I have no design upon you, nor any upon the Face of the Earth; nor have I ever sought or received any worldly Gain or Advantage to my self, by any Testimony I have at any time appeared in, (but on the contrary have largely suffered,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:104194:14"/> and do suffer upon that very account) nor have I propounded any such thing to my self hereby, for I have been grieved that this oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casion was given by this Author (a person whom I never knew) and in secret I much desired some other might be stirred up to wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness against it, till I felt it in my Spirit a Work and Testimony re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired of me, wherein I must clear my Conscience in the sight of God, to whom I must give account; and I have not studied to find out Arguments whereby to run down the Simplest Man or Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man in the least measure of Truth, neither do I hereby desire, nor seek to acquire a Name or Esteem among Men, nor strive for Mastery or Victory in Controversie; for I am very sensible that my time is near to an end, and my day near expired, in which I find it my weighty concern to be found doing and suffering what the Lord calls me unto, by and through the assistance of his holy Spirit and Power, concerning which I must give an account to him, and receive Reward accordingly.</p>
               <p>And now to all People I do declare, that I stedfastly believe that all Profession of Religion, and outward Performances and Observa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, received by Tradition or Imitation of others, Comprehend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and Practiced in the carnal mind, doth not avail to Salvation, nor that the Imitation of <hi>John's</hi> Water-Baptism, tho a true Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stration in its time, by him that was truly called and sent of God to fulfil that Ministry, wherein he bore Record and Testimony of a greater, who was to come after him, tho he was before him, <hi>who should Baptize with the holy Ghost and with Fire,</hi> (mark) <hi>and with his Fan thoroughly purge his Floor, and gather the Wheat into the Garner, and burn the Chaff with unquenchable Fire,</hi> (mark, a great work) <hi>Mat.</hi> 3.12. And this Baptizer, and Baptism the Apostles preached, and the Primitive <hi>Christians</hi> witnessed, in which they were buried with Christ, Baptized into Christ, and put on Christ, and were new Creatures: and this Dipping or Plunging in Water cannot do, and without which, outward things did not then, nor do now avail any thing.</p>
               <p>And tho in that time they did somtimes Baptize with Water, as also some did Circumcize, Shave, Vow and condescended to such like legal Observations, among them that were Zealous of the Law and Ordinances, once commanded to the <hi>Jews,</hi> that they might gain the <hi>Jews</hi> and those that were under the Law, yet they plainly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared that none of these things availed, but <hi>a new Creature,</hi> and
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:104194:14"/>
                  <hi>Faith which works by Love, and that Christ is all, and all one in him,</hi> Gal. 6.15. Chap. 3.27,28. Col 3.11. <hi>And that the Baptism that now saves us, is not the puting away of the filth of the Flesh, but the answer of a good Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science towards God, by the Resurrection of Jesus Christ,</hi> 1 Pet. 3.21. And this cannot be attained by an Imitation of that which was a true Ministration, before he was made manifest to <hi>Israel,</hi> whom <hi>John</hi> knew not, till he that sent him to Baptize with Water, said unto him, <hi>That upon whom he should see the Spirit descending, and remaining on him, the same is he that Baptizeth with the holy Ghost; and he saw and bare Record that this is the Son of God,</hi> John 1.31,33,34.</p>
               <p>So now my desire is, that both Old and Young People, and Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, may cease from following the Deceivers of all sorts, who for Gain, and worldly Advantage, by their cunning C <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aftiness deceive the simple, in drawing their minds from the true Light of Christ Jesus, or the holy Spirit of Truth in their own Hearts, by calling it <hi>delusion, insufficient,</hi> &amp;c. And the Testimony of it <hi>evil, pernicious, cursed</hi> and <hi>Popish Doctrine;</hi> for so were the Prophets of old, Christ and the Apostles treated, and most by them that made the highest pretences to the Law, Scriptures and Ordinances, and were Zealous Contenders in a false Spirit. But in all Generations, who were turned to the Light, or Measure of the Spirit of Christ in their own Hearts, and in sincerity of Heart receive the same, and came true<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to walk and abide therein, none were ever deluded or mis-led by it, which leads out of Sin, and every sinful way, into Truth and Holiness, without which none can come to God: But all that ever have been drawn out from it, to follow self-ended and deceitful men (tho never so covered with Profession of Religion, and feigned words) have been thereby deceived, as by their Fruits is clearly manifest.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>Written in <hi>York-Castle,</hi> where I am detained Prisoner for Obeying the Command of Christ, who saith, <hi>Swear not at all.</hi>
                     <date>The 1st Day of the 10th Month, 1691.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="postscript">
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:104194:15"/>
               <head>Postscript.</head>
               <p>ANd forasmuch as many in this Generation, (some through Envy, and others through Ignorance) have often reproach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and slandered us, as if we were a People not believing the Scriptures, which is altogether false; It is in my Heart, (not as insulting over any, but in tenderness to all where this may come) to propound a few places of Scripture to your Serious Consideration, whether ye do indeed believe the Testimony there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of to be true.</p>
               <p>One Place is that of <hi>Mat.</hi> 12.34. <hi>How can ye, being Evil, speak Good things; for out of the abundance of the Heart the Mouth speaketh?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now consider this all ye that say, tho the publick Teachers be Proud, Covetous and unjust Men, and many of them Voluptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and Vicious, and so manifest themselves to be evil, <hi>yet</hi> (say you) <hi>They Teach well, and Speak good things.</hi> Now this Imagination is absolutely contrary to this Scripture-Testimony of our Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus Christ: I own that the Scriptures being the words of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, Christ and the Apostles, are good Words, and a Testimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of good things, holy Men of God spake as they were moved by the good and holy Spirit, and for good ends, <hi>viz.</hi> to draw and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swade People to God; but when corrupt deceitful Men speaks the same words, with their Comments, Additions, Glosses, and Mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, to draw People after them for filthy Lucre, these are not good things, nor doth the hearing them profit People at all.</p>
               <p>Another Sculpture is of <hi>Mat.</hi> 12. <hi>ver.</hi> 36. <hi>I say unto you, that every Idle Word that Men shall speak, they shall give Account thereof at the Day of Judgment.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now consider this all ye Scoffers, Jesters, Romancers, wanton and debauched Talkers, do ye believe this Scripture to be true? then its high time for you to leave these Practices, least you add to your account till ye be not able to answer in the dreadful Day of God.</p>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:104194:15"/>
               <p>Another Scripture is, 1 Thess. 4.6. <hi>That no Man go beyond or defraud his Brother in any matter, because the Lord is the Avenger of all such.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Hear this now all ye who bend your Wit to cheat, defraud, cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumvent, and go beyond them you deal withal, of which there is at this Day so great a cry against one another in matters both of Law and Trade; if ye believe this Scripture to be true, its time to cease from these deceitful Practices, lest by continuance therein ye heap up Vengeance against your own Souls, more then you shall be able to bear.</p>
               <p>Another Scripture is in 2 Cor. 5.10. <hi>For we must all appear before the Judgment-Seat of Christ, that every one may receive the things done in the Body, according to that he hath done, whether it be good or bad.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now all People that read and hear the Scriptures, consider Seri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ously if ye believe this Testimony, and live in the sence of that belief, bad Words and Deeds would not so abound where <hi>Christia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity</hi> and Belief of the Scriptures is professed in Words.</p>
               <p>So now Dear People, my Souls travel is, that ye my Country-Men whom the Lord hath favoured with the knowledge and free use of the Scriptures of Truth, may truly recieve, believe and obey the holy Spirit of our Lord Jesus Christ in your own Hearts and Consciences, by which the Scriptures were given forth, that thereby your understandings may be opened, to know the things that weightily concern the eternal Salvation of your own Souls, and that by it your Lives and Conversations may be ordered, to live and walk, and have your Consciences exercised towards God and men at all times, and in all things, as a People so believing, being tru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ly zealous of good Works, and so obtain the good Reward through our Lord Jesus Christ, who is the Author of Eternal Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation to all that truly believe, sincerely obey, faithfully follow and abide in him.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>S. E.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>